Guide to the Nelson Hayes Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Nelson Hayes Papers
1913-1973
1925-1973
YCAL MSS 386
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
14.8
(37 boxes)
The Nelson Hayes papers contain correspondence, writings, journals, and other materials documenting the personal and professional life of author Nelson Hayes.
Hayes, Nelson, 1903-1971
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Hayes estate, 1973.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Nelson Hayes (1903-)
Nelson Hayes was born October 9, 1903, in Trépied, Pas de Calais, France, son of Chester Coleman and Henrietta (Andrews) Hayes. He attended the Hotchkiss School and Yale (class of 1925) before marrying Emmy Katherine Clason on December 28, 1925. Hayes's professional employment included work as a secretary and assistant teasurer at Lockwood Manufacturing Co. in South Norwalk, CT (1925-1930), a real estate broker in South Norwalk, CT (1934-1955), and an investment executive in Roxbury, VT (1955-).
Scope and Contents
The Nelson Hayes papers contain correspondence, writings, journals, and other materials documenting the personal and professional life of author Nelson Hayes. Materials throughout the collection also document Hayes's special interest in the Caribbean. For example, subject files located in the Correspondence and Personal Papers series, writings, and journals contain clippings, personal observations and commentary, and photographs relating to the Caribbean. Specific writings set in the Caribbean include "Caribbean Junket", Dildo Cay, and "Spanceled". Otherwise, the bulk of the general correspondence in the collection is with Hayes's wife, mother, and two daughters. Correspondence relating to writings consists chiefly of letters from editors about novels, short stories, articles, and other writings. The Writings series contains research files and drafts for various forms of work, such as articles, poems, short stories, and published and unpublished novels. There are typescript copies of Hayes's journals, including research for writings, lists of illustrations, and indices, dating from 1950 to 1970; journals are bound with original correspondence, photographs, and clippings dating from 1922 to 1973. Personal Papers contain a calendar, clippings, and notebooks.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1915-1973. II. Writings, 1920-1973. III. Journals, undated. IV. Personal Papers, 1971.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Authors; Hayes, Nelson, 1903-1971
- Correspondence, 1915-1973; Series I; 6.67; (16 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: General Correspondence and Correspondence Relating to Writings.
  Scope and Contents
  General correspondence includes family, personal, and professional correspondence. The bulk of the correspondence is with Hayes's wife ("Emmy"), mother, and two daughters ("Ilse" and "Larrier"). There are also subject files on "Public Issues" and the "Virgin Islands" containing correspondence and clippings.
  Correspondence Relating to Writings, arranged alphabetically, consists chiefly of letters from editors about novels, short stories, articles, and other writings. There is also correspondence with literary agents and fan mail. The largest group of letters relates to Hayes's best-known novel Dildo Cay.
  The correspondence contains some newspaper clippings, notes, and writings.
  Additional correspondence can be found among the journals in Series III.
  - General Correspondence
    - Andrews, C. B., 1925-1953; 2 (Box 1)
    - Davies, A. Mervyn, 1936-1939 (Box 1)
    - Dickson, Lovat, 1935-1939 (Box 1)
    - Dupuch, Sir Etienne, 1968-1971 (Box 1)
    - Giovine, Larrier H. (daughter), 1953-1957 (Box 1)
    - Giovine, Larrier H. (daughter), 1943-1971; 6 (Box 2)
    - Giovine, Larrier H. (daughter), 1957-1971; 6 (Box 3)
    - Giovine, Larrier H. (daughter), 1963-1970; 4 (Box 4)
    - Goddard, George McGill Hayes, 1967-1971 (Box 4)
    - Goddard, Elizabeth Hayes, 1962-1966 (Box 5)
    - Govoni, Ilse Hayes (daughter), 1942-1949; 4 (Box 5)
    - Govoni, Ilse Hayes (daughter), 1950-1959; 9 (Box 6)
    - Govoni, Ilse Hayes (daughter), 1960-1971; 7 (Box 7)
    - Hayes, Chester C., 1915-1947; 5 (Box 8)
    - Hayes, Chester C., 1937-1948 (Box 9)
    - Hayes, Emmy (wife), 1923-1933; 3 (Box 9)
    - Hayes, Emmy (wife), 1931-1950; 5 (Box 10)
    - Hayes, Emmy (wife), 1949-1973; 5 (Box 11)
    - Hayes, Dr. George, 1925-1953; 2 (Box 11)
    - Hayes (General), 1936-1941 (Box 11)
    - Hayes, H. A. (mother), 1919-1936; 5 (Box 12)
    - Hayes, H. A. (mother), 1952-1961; 2 (Box 13)
    - Hayes, Posie Hammond, 1920-1972; 2 (Box 13)
    - Hayes Goddard, Elizabeth, 1962-1972 (Box 13)
    - Public Issues, 1943-1971, undated; 2 (Box 13)
    - Virgin Islands, 1934 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence Relating to Writings
    - Agents and Magazines, 1951-1958 (Box 13)
    - Articles, 1965-1970 (Box 13)
    - Autob. Journal, 1971 (Box 13)
    - "Beauty at a Bargain", 1948-1951 (Box 13)
    - The Bermudian, 1932-1934 (Box 13)
    - "Blockade", 1930-1940 (Box 14)
    - "A Bout With a Bear", 1950-1951 (Box 14)
    - "A Cabin in the Wilderness", 1947-1951 (Box 14)
    - Destiny of an Indian Village, 1933-1945 (Box 14)
    - Dildo Cay, 1939-1950; 7 (Box 14)
    - "First Buck", 1948-1949 (Box 14)
    - Guns and Hunting, 1966-1970 (Box 14)
    - Hayes, Nelson, 1930 (Box 14)
    - Houghton Mifflin Co., 1936-1946 (Box 14)
    - Houghton Mifflin Co., 1936-1946 (Box 15)
    - "An Island of Our Own", 1963-1970; 3 (Box 15)
    - Magazines, 1947-1951 (Box 15)
    - "Marcus Aurelius", 1968-1971 (Box 15)
    - "Mayday in March", 1968-1971 (Box 15)
    - Meador, Frank, 1947-1948 (Box 15)
    - "The Nature of the Beast", 1968-1970 (Box 15)
    - "Operation Hemorrhoids", 1949-1950 (Box 15)
    - Otis, Elizabeth (agent), 1946-1947 (Box 15)
    - "Point of Departure", 1965-1967 (Box 15)
    - Portraits, Inc., 1953 February 18 (Box 15)
    - Prominent people, 1928-1949 (Box 15)
    - The Roof of the Wind, 1961-1968; 3 (Box 15)
    - Saunders, Marion (agent), 1943-1947 (Box 15)
    - Shipway, George, 1969-1971 (Box 15)
    - "Small Fry", 1950-1951 (Box 15)
    - "Spanceled", 1947-1951 (Box 16)
    - "Stronghold of Sail", 1971 (Box 16)
    - Vermont Life, 1954 (Box 16)
    - "The Weaning of Laura Treat", 1947-1951 (Box 16)
    - The Writer, 1954 (Box 16)
    - Yachting, 1955-1961; 4 (Box 16)
    - Writing (miscellaneous), 1933, undated; 14 (Box 16)
- Writings, 1920-1973; Series II; 5.63; (14 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Series II, Writings, contains research files and drafts for various forms of work, such as articles, poems, short stories, and published and unpublished novels. Aside from early notes and poems dating from Hayes's time as a student at Yale, most writings date from the early 1930s to early 1970s.
  - "Afloat and Ashore", undated (Box 17)
  - "An Afternoon With Dr. Beebe", 1973 December (Box 17)
  - "America Acquitted", 1931 November (Box 17)
  - "As a Matter of Fact", 1932 February (Box 17)
  - "Bid For Freedom", undated; 3 (Box 17)
  - Block prints, undated; 3 (Box 17)
  - Blockade, 1933, undated; 2 (Box 17)
  - "Brass-Wing", 1973 December (Box 18)
  - Church Story, 1967 April 16 (Box 18)
  - "The Dedication of St. Anne's", 1968 November 24 (Box 18)
  - "The Enemy Within", 1970 August 29 (Box 18)
  - Five Novels Monthly story, 1931 October (Box 18)
  - "Four O'Clock Needle", 1932 (Box 18)
  - "Going Through", 1932 March (Box 18)
  - "His Own Funeral", 1931 August (Box 18)
  - "An Island of Our Own", undated; 6 (Box 18)
  - "Caribbean Junket", 1940
  - "An Island of Our Own", undated; 1 (Box 19)
  - "Last Stand in Vermont", 1940 (Box 19)
  - "The Last of El Porvenir", 1931 February (Box 19)
  - "Log Cabin", 1947 (Box 19)
  - "The Man Who Wouldn't Work", 1931 August (Box 19)
  - "Marcus Aurelius", 1964-1970, undated; 6 (Box 20)
  - "A Mayday in March", undated (Box 21)
  - "Murder on Noomea", 1930 (Box 21)
  - "Nature of the Beast", 1971 (Box 21)
  - Notes for New Stories, 1954, undated (Box 21)
  - "The Old Woman and the Sea", 1955 (Box 21)
  - "On Cruising the Bahamas", undated (Box 21)
  - "On the Rebound", undated (Box 21)
  - "Operation Hemorrhoids", 1973 December (Box 21)
  - "Our Master 85", undated (Box 21)
  - "The Pequot Captives", undated (Box 21)
  - Poems, Early, 1923-1926 (Box 21)
  - "Point of Departure", undated (Box 21)
  - Reviews, 1935-1940 (Box 21)
  - Rhapsody in Andros, 1952; 2 (Box 21)
  - "Rhythmic Variation and the Natural Manner in Prose", undated (Box 21)
  - The Roof of the Wind, 1955-1960; 3 (Box 22)
  - "Small Fry", 1951, undated; 2 (Box 22)
  - "Spanceled", 1939-1958, undated; 4 (Box 23)
  - "Spanceled", 1950-1951; 2 (Box 24)
  - "Spanceled", 1956-1957; 2 (Box 25)
  - "Spanceled", 1961, 1963; 2 (Box 26)
  - "Squid", 1930 August 7 (Box 26)
  - "A Stranger's Sojourn", 1970-1971; 3 (Box 27)
  - "A Stranger's Sojourn", 1972 (Box 28)
  - "The Surest Way to Get Your Buck", undated (Box 28)
  - "T. E. W. B. T.", undated (Box 28)
  - "Unearthed", 1931-1932; 2 (Box 28)
  - "The Way of a Man", 1931 February (Box 29)
  - "The Weaning of Laura Treat", 1952 (Box 29)
  - "What Would You Have Done?", undated (Box 29)
  - "What's Wrong", 1963-1964 (Box 29)
  - "White Lies", 1930 (Box 29)
  - "Whitetails", undated (Box 29)
  - "Why My Mother Remarried", 1931 July (Box 29)
  - "The Winner", undated (Box 29)
  - "Woodcock", 1966 (Box 29)
  - Fragments, notes, etc., 1920-1925, undated; 3 (Box 29)
- Journals, 1950-1973; Series III; 2.29; (6 boxes)
  Arranged chronologically.
  Series III, Journals, contains typescript copies of Hayes's journals covering the period from 1950 to 1970. Journals include research for writings, lists of illustrations, and indices, and are bound with original correspondence, photographs, and clippings dating from 1922 to 1973. Volumes are numbered in chronological order, with individual titles listed in folder headings below. The dates of the period covered are given in brackets, though inscriptions suggest that copies may have been made at a later date.
  - I-II. Crisis in Paradise, [1950-1951]; 2 (Box 30)
  - III. Rhapsody in Andros, [1951] (Box 30)
  - IV. Rhapsody in Andros, [1951-1952] (Box 31)
  - V. Interlude, [1953] (Box 31)
  - VI. The Sea Beast Adventure, [1953-1954] (Box 31)
  - VII-IX. The Sea Beast Adventure, [1953-1954]; 3 (Box 32)
  - X. The Difficult Baby Box, [1956-1957] (Box 33)
  - XI. Ordeal By Storm, [1951-1960] (Box 33)
  - XII. Ordeal by Storm, [1960-1967] (Box 34)
  - XIII. The Enemy Within, [1965-1970] (Box 34)
  - XIV. Afterglow, [1970-1973] (Box 35)
- Personal Papers, 1913-1971; Series IV; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by topic.
  Series IV, Personal Papers, contains a calendar, clippings or subject files on the Bahamas and the West, and notebooks. Additional clippings on "Public Issues" and the "Virgin Islands" can be found with general correspondence in Series I.
  - Calendar, undated (Box 36)
  - Clippings, 1971; 2 (Box 36)
  - Notebooks, [circa 1913], undated (Box 36)
- Oversize, 0.21; (1 box)
  - "Caribbean Junket", 1940 (Box 37)